It’s very difficult to wonder about
انه من الصعب جدا ان ’ التلاميذ حول
life, our lives, life on this planet,
الحياة , حياتنا , الحياة على هذا الكوكب
and life on other planets, without first
والحياة على الكواكب الاخرى , بدون اولا
wondering about stars.
اتساءل عن النجوم .
Stars are the substance, the engines that build
النجوم , وهي مادة بناء المحركات التي
everything in our known universe.
كل شيء في الكون .
And without understanding stars, we will
وبدون فهم , سالنجوم
never understand where planets come from
لم نفهم اين تاتي من الكواكب
and where we came from.
ومن اين اتينا .
We have one star that we’ve been able to
لدينا اننا ’ ve نجم واحد ل
study in exquisite detail, and that’s the Sun
دراسة في التفاصيل , والتي طغت ’ التلاميذ الشمس
and that’s because it’s so close by.
وهذا ’ التلاميذ ’ التلاميذ لانها قريبة من قبل .
You can actually take pictures of it
يمكنك اخذ الصور منه
and be able to see sunspots
ويكون قادرا على رؤية sunspots
and see solar explosions. And
ونري explosions. والطاقة الشمسية
the Sun is the only star that we’ve
الشمس هو اننا فقط ’ ve النجم
been able to look at in this sort of detail.
نستطيع ان ننظر الى في هذا النوع من التفاصيل .
And this is where you need special
وهذا هو المكان الذي نحتاج مميز
techniques to look at other stars
لننظر الى تقنيات النجوم الاخرى
and see them in the sort of detail that has
ورؤيتهم في هذا النوع من التفاصيل
been previously only done for the Sun.
فقط كانت في السابق للشمس .
CHARA stands for Center for High
للchara عالية
Angular Resolution Astronomy,
علم الفلك , رسم الدقة
which basically is the theme of what we do.
واساسا هو موضوع ما نفعله .
Resolution is the ability to see fine detail
الحل هو القدرة على رؤية التفاصيل الدقيقة
in distant objects, and unfortunately,
في الاجسام البعيدة , وللاسف ,
distances are so great in astronomy
في علم الفلك لمسافات
that resolution has always been
ان الحل كان دوما
something that has been unattainable
شيء تم unattainable
for most of the objects we look at.
بالنسبة لمعظم الاشياء نظرنا .
Stars, for example, are so far away
النجوم , على سبيل المثال , اذا بعيدا
that even with the biggest
انه حتى مع اكبر
telescopes that we've ever built
التلسكوبات التي قمنا بها على الاطلاق
most of them appear just as points
معظمها تبدو كما نقاط
of light. But the kind of problems
من light. ولكن هذا النوع من المشاكل
that we have to solve involving
تلك التي لدينا لحل
measuring sizes of stars
قياس الحجم من النجوم
requires us to build telescopes that
لاننا نبني تلسكوبات يتطلب
are not just tens of meters across,
ليست فقط عبر عشرات الامتار ,
but hundreds of meters across, and
ولكن , وعبر مئات الامتار
those are completely unfeasible
تلك هي unfeasible تماما
for the indefinite future.
indefinite للمستقبل .
So we get around this problem by
لذا علينا حول هذه المشكلة
synthesizing a single giant telescope
التلسكوب عملاقة تصنيع واحد
with arrays of smaller telescopes.
مع اصغر من التلسكوبات محولات .